Guide to the Barry Miles Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Barry Miles Papers,
1958-1990
Miles, Barry, 1943-
16 linear feet (37 boxes: 27 document boxes, 10 cassette tape boxes, 1 flat file).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4078472
The Barry Miles Papers contains correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, and printed materials concerned with Miles' literary activities in the London counterculture. Included are letters and manuscripts from William S. Burroughs and Allen Ginsberg, among numerous others. This collection also includes material used by Miles in the research and writing of his work Ginsberg: A Biography as well as from his editorship of the annotated edition of Ginsberg’s Howl.
Biographical Note
Barry Miles was born in 1943, in Cirencester, England. He studied art at Cheltenham College of Art before moving to London and qualifying as an art teacher.
Throughout the 1960s, Miles managed Better Books, a counterculture center located in London, at which he staged performances and poetry readings of American poets, helping to generate greater interest in American literary and arts movements within Britain.
After Better Books was sold in 1965, and Miles, together with art critic John Dunbar and musician Peter Asher, founded MAD Ltd. With the financial support of Paul McCartney, they opened Indica Bookshop and Art Gallery in 1966, which continued to host experimental poetry readings and avant-garde art shows. Miles remained owner/manager of Indica until it closed in 1970.
Also around this time, Miles founded and edited a number of little magazines, including Trees and The Long Hair Times (also, sometimes, just Long Hair), magazines that specialized in publishing Beat poetry and other avant-garde and experimental literature from the US and UK. The latter magazine was the direct forerunner of the underground newspaper The International Times (later just IT), founded in 1966 by Miles, John “Hoppy” Hopkins, and Jim Haynes.
Miles became manager of Zapple Records in 1968, a subsidiary of the Beatles’ Apple Records, which was intended as an outlet for spoken word and avant-garde records. Only two records were released before Zapple folded in 1969.
Living in New York for much of the 1970s, Miles worked for Allen Ginsberg catalogueing his tape archives and writing for New Musical Express. He later returned to London to edit Time Out.
Since the 1970s, Miles has worked as a writer and biographer, and in 1989 he published the first complete biography of Allen Ginsberg. He has also written biographies of Paul McCartney, Frank Zappa, William S Burroughs, Jack Kerouac, and Charles Bukowski, and the band Pink Floyd, as well as editing annotated editions of Ginsberg’s Howl and Burroughs’ Naked Lunch. He has written extensively on the Sixties counterculture, publishing the book Hippie and an essay in I Want to Take You Higher: The Psychedelic Era, 1965-1969.
Scope and Content
This collection is comprised of the correspondence and manuscripts (primarily of others) obtained by Miles in his capacity as a bookseller at Better Books and Indica Bookshop, little magazine publisher (The International Times, Longhair), and producer at Zapple Records from the mid-1960s through the 1990s. Also included is material compiled by Miles during the writing of Ginsberg: A Biography, and the annotated edition of Ginsberg’s Howl, including multiple drafts of these writings.
The bulk of the correspondence pertains to Miles’ publishing and bookselling efforts, much of it from counterculture poets and writers. William S Burroughs and Allen Ginsberg are the most voluminous of Mile’s correspondents. Also included are many flyers and catalogues.
The manuscript holdings consist largely of poetry, although there are a number of prose works by William S Burroughs. There are also a large number of Ginsberg manuscripts.
The scholarly work of Miles himself are also found in this collection, primarily drafts and research materials for Ginsberg: A Biography, and the annotated edition of Howl. There are ten distinct versions of the former work, along with handwritten research notes, typed chronologies and itineraries, and duplicate Ginsberg correspondences and journals from university libraries and personal collections. Included are ten boxes of cassette tapes of Ginsberg readings, lectures, and interviews.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 5 series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1960s-1980s
Series II. Manuscripts, 1959-1979
Series III. Allen Ginsberg, 1960s-1990s
Series IV. Ginsberg: A Biography Materials, 1943-2000
Series V. Annotated Howl, 1955-1986
Subjects
Ferlinghetti, Lawrence.; Patten, Brian, 1946-; Malanga, Gerard.; McClure, Michael.; Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Brautigan, Richard.; Booksellers and bookselling.; Little magazines--England--London.; Poetry.; Advertsements.; Announcements.; Bibliographies.; Broadsides.; Brochures.; Catalogs (trade).; Collages.; Drafts (literary).; Drawings.; Essays.; Galley proofs.; Genealogies.; Handbills.; Indexes.; Interviews.; Invitations.; Itineraries.; Manuscripts (literary).; Notes.; Photographs.; Photoprints.; Poems.; Posters.; Press releases.; Resumes.; Reviews.; Silkscreen prints.; Artists.; Authors.2lcsh; Biographers.; Editors.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
08/15/86 M-86-08-15 297-2/17/86; 2/24/86; 8/15/86 Purchase.
07/22/92 M-92-07-22 Allen Ginsberg letters & misc. 293 Purchase
Alternate Formats
William Burroughs letters are available on microfilm.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1960s-1980s
  This series contains correspondence related to Miles’ work as a publisher of the little magazines Longhair and The International Times, and as owner and manager of London’s Better Books and Indica Books. Most of the correspondents are writers and artists from the counterculture scene in the US and Britain.
  The majority of the correspondents are represented by only one or two letters, primarily addressing business and promotional concerns. These are arranged alphabetically within “General Correspondence.” Because some of the correspondents are people of note, this finding aid includes a list of correspondents found within the “General Correspondents” folders.
  Correspondents with a large volume of material have been filed individually, the largest of these being the correspondence of William S Burroughs, which is also available on microfilm in the Columbia University library catalogue.
  Original flyers and catalogues for various little magazines, book publications, poetry readings, and musical events have also been placed within this series.
  All materials have been organized alphabetically by correspondent.
  - General, 1960s-1980s (8 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 8)
  - General--List of Correspondents, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Berrigan, Ted, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brautigan, Richard, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Burroughs, William S., 1967-1983 (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 12 to 13)
    (Microfilm available.)
  - Burroughs Book Project, 1966-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Di Prima, Diane, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Horovitz, Michael, 1969-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - McGilvery, Laurence, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Malanga, Gerard, 1965-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Maynard, Joe, 1973--1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mikriammos, Philippe, 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Olson, Charles, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pivano, Fernanda, 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sanders, Ed, 1965-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Catalogues and Flyers, 1965-1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series II: Manuscripts, 1959-1979
  This series holds the manuscripts of writers associated with Miles and his various magazines (Long Hair and Trees), as well as his publishing, promotional, recording (at Zapple Records), and bookselling ventures. There are no manuscripts by Miles himself in this series, however, there are a considerable number of original manuscripts by William S Burroughs here.
  All manuscripts have been arranged alphabetically.
  - General, 1959-1979 (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Burroughs, William S., 1965-1976
    - Intro to Miles Biography, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - “MOB”, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - “St. Louis Return”, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - “Who Is the Written Third Walks Beside You”, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - DiPrima, Diane--“Ode to Keats” and “Revolutionary Letters”, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Horovitz, Michael, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Malanga, Gerard, 1964-1965
    - Clockwork, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - General, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Shepp, Archie--“SCAG,” 1965 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Warhol, Andy, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series III: Allen Ginsberg, 1960s-1990s
  Correspondence, as well as manuscripts and typescript drafts of poems by Allen Ginsberg, are included in this series. There can also be found a handwritten itinerary of one of Ginsberg’s reading tours, and Ginsberg’s rendition of his family tree that includes a sketch by Beat poet Gregory Corso. These materials have been organized alphabetically.
  - Correspondence 1960s-1980s (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Correspondence, 1970s-1990s (4 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 4 to 7)
    (1992 Addition)
  - Manuscripts, 1973-1982
    - “Airplane Blues,” 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - “Capitol Air,” 1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - “Conversation Sanders,” 1980 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - “Do the Meditation; Rock Rag,” 1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - “Dope Fiend Blues,” 1974 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Family Tree, with Gregory Corso pencil drawing, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - “Gospel Noble Truths,” 1975 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Itinerary, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - “Psalm on My Illness,” 1973 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Series IV: Ginsberg: A Biography Materials, 1943-2000
  This series consists of materials related to Barry Miles’ biography of Allen Ginsberg. First, it includes ten distinct manuscript drafts of the biography itself, up to and including galleys and typeset drafts. Many of these drafts include handwritten notes and corrections. The sixth draft has extensive corrections by Ginsberg. There is also a draft of the revised edition of the biography. Additionally, a published copy of the first edition, signed and annotated throughout by Ginsberg, can be found.
  The research materials are quite extensive, including typed chronologies of Ginsberg’s life, and itineraries of his various travels, as well as transcribed interviews with family and friends.
  Audio recordings of interviews are also in this series, part of a 10-box collection of cassette tapes containing duplicates of tapes from Ginsberg’s personal collection. The cassette tapes are ordered according to Ginsberg’s own organizational schema when possible. Other audio material, such as Miles’ interviews with Ginsberg friends and family, are arranged alphabetically by interviewee.
  There is also Miles’ detailed year-by-year chronological reconstruction of Ginsberg’s life, from 1943 to Ginsberg’s death in 1997. These files contain contemporary newspaper clippings; selected Ginsberg journal entries; letters regarding relevant details of Ginsberg’s life; writings by Ginsberg and others from the year specified; and studies of Ginsberg and the Beats relevant to that year. Within the folder ‘Year 1949’ can be found photocopies of Ginsberg’s early manuscript “The Fall.”
  Nearly all of this material is photocopied. The duplicated material is dated, in the container list, by when the originals were produced; the photocopies themselves date from the 1980s, the period when Miles was writing the biography.
  This series also contains extensive correspondence, some related to the publication of the biography, but mostly a collection of Ginsberg’s personal correspondence from the 1940s to the 1990s. As with the chronological material discussed above, this correspondence is almost exclusively photocopied Also found within this series are duplicates of Ginsberg’s journals from 1953 to 1980. Finally, this series contains a small collection of Ginsberg obituaries.
  - Archive Sale, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Audio Material--Cassette Tapes (Box 28-35)
    - Allen Ginsberg's Collection, 1959-1988 (137 Tapes) (Box 28-35)
    - Ball, Gordon - Whalen, Phillip--Tape 1, 1984-1986 (17 Tapes) (Box 36)
    - Whalen, Phillip --Tape 2, 1986 (1 Tape) (Box 37)
    - Recordings of Allen Ginsberg, 1967-1990 (11 Tapes) (Box 37)
  - Background Material and Autobiographical Precis, circa 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Childhood Notes, 1970s (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Chronology, 1943-1997
    - General, 1970-1980s (6 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 3 to 8)
    - Year-by-Year
      - 1943-1999 (3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 9 to 11)
      - 1943-1997 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - 1944-1999 (Box 4, Folder 13)
        - General Notes, 1953-1980s (Box 4, Folder 14)
        - Carr, Lucien, 1944s-1999 (Box 4, Folder 15)
          - Allen Ginsberg Novel and Conversation Transcripts, 1944-1999 (Box 4, Folder 16)
          - Clippings, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - 1945-1999, (4 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 2 to 5)
      - 1949-1997
        - General, 1949 (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 6 to 7)
        - “The Fall”--Notebooks, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - 1950-1997, (3 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 9 to 12)
      - 1953-2000 (9 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1 to 9)
      - 1962-1999, (14 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 14)
      - 1976-1978 (3 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1 to 3)
      - 1979
        - General, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 4)
        - Allen Ginsberg--European Itinerary, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - 1980-1993, (6 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 6 to 11)
      - 1986-1997, (11 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 1 to 11)
  - Collected Poems Footnotes, Undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1999
    - Biography-Related, 1976-1990
      - General, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Libraries, 1976-1987 (Box 10, Folder 14)
      - Simon & Schuster, 1988-1990 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Ginsberg, 1943-1999
      - Burroughs, William S., 1950-1999 (4 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 1 to 4)
      - General
        - 1943-1950, (3 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 5 to 7)
        - 1951-1960 (8 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 1 to 8)
        - 1961-1978 (12 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 1 to 12)
        - 1990-1996 (9 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 1 to 9)
      - Miles, 1966-1979 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Drafts, 1980s-2000
    - First Draft
      - Chapters 1-4, circa 1980s (4 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 11 to 14)
      - Chapters 5-21, circa 1980s (17 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 1 to 17)
      - Chapters 22-25, circa 1980s (4 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 1 to 4)
    - Second Draft
      - Chapters 1-3, circa 1980s (3 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 5 to 7)
    - Third Draft
      - Chapters 1-8, circa 1980s (8 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 8 to 15)
      - Chapters 9-22, circa 1980s (14 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 1 to 14)
      - Chapters 23-29, circa 1980s (7 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 1 to 7)
      - Chapters 30-33, circa 1980s (4 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 1 to 4)
    - Fourth Draft
      - Chapters 1-2, circa 1980s (2 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 5 to 6)
      - Chapter 3, circa 1980s (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Fifth Draft 1988 (2 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Sixth Draft
      - circa 1980s (4 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 4 to 7)
      - circa 1980s (2 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 1 to 2)
      - circa 1980s, (Oversize) (Box 273)
    - Final--Copyedited, 1988 (4 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 3 to 6)
    - Galleys, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Galleys, 1989 (2 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 1 to 2)
    - First Typeset Photocopy, 1989 (3 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 3 to 5)
    - Afterword, circa 1980s (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Index, circa 1980s (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Published First Edition, signed by Ginsberg, with marginalia, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - English Edition, 2000 (2 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 8 to 9)
    - English Edition, 2000 (3 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Family Notes, 1980s-1999
    - Naomi (Mother), 1987-1999 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Louis (Father), 1980s-1999 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Interviews--Transcribed, 1980s
    - Friends and Family, circa 1986 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Ginsberg, Allen, 1985-1986 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Interview Questions, Undated (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Journals, 1953-1980
    (Photocopied Material)
    - 1953-1958 (4 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 9 to 12)
    - 1958-1964 (9 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 1 to 9)
    - 1965-1973 (8 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 1 to 8)
    - 1973-1985 (5 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 1 to 5)
  - Kaddish
    - Origins, 1950s-1960s (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Filmscript, Undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Playscript, 1972 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Obituaries, 1997-1999 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Recordings Listings and Liner Notes, 1971-1993 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Russia, Undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Stanford University Notes, 1999 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Vollmer, Joan, 1951 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - University of Texas Ginsberg Collection Notes, Undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
- Series V: Annotated Howl, 1955-1986
  In 1986, Miles edited an annotated, facsimile edition of Ginsberg’s Howl. In addition to a number of unpublished drafts, this series contains annotations, appendices, and other materials contained within the book. There are also photocopies of Ginsberg letters and correspondence between Miles and the book publishers.
  - Annotations, 1985 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Appendix 1: Ginsberg Correspondences, 1955-1958 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Appendices--Other, Undated (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Book Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Front Matter, Undated (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Unpublished Materials, Undated (Box 27, Folder 12)